[Music]
Hello, everyone.
TDSW YouTube Channel.
Getting started with GLSL on TouchDesigner, the second episode
Thank you for watching!
This time, sir.
Coordinates, explain the coordinate system and
The end result is something as cool as what you're seeing right now.
I'd like to make a few things.
GLSL
I'll use this.
It's a GLSL coordinate system.
It's what's called a right-handed coordinate system.
x is + when going right.
The higher up you go, the more + y is in the wind
We're supposed to deal with values from 0 to 1 in this one.
Bottom left is x = 0 and y = 0
The top right corner becomes x =1 y=1
And while we're at it, the top left-hand corner is.
x =0 y=1
The bottom right corner says x=1 y=0
It's like this.
You can easily visualize these in GLSL with color, so you can use
I'd like to take a look at it.
I opened GLSL with an external editor.
I'd like to put it here and lay it out.
What we're going to use here is this variable called vUV.
What is this?
Now this is a 256x256 texture.
There's a pixel in there.
It contains information on all the coordinates.
Basically, this is TouchDesigner's
This function is supposed to be available in GLSL TOP
When combining the Fragment Shader and the Vertex Shader, you can use
From the Vertex Shader by yourself.
I'd have to send you a variable.
You don't have to think about that, especially in this case.
It's got a "st" on the back.
This is something called Swizzle.
It's used to represent these vector and other values.
Besides st.
It's called rgba or xyz.
For example.
This vec4 color is called
vec4(1.0), so there are four rgba and
So it's all going to be with one in it.
When you take this out.
Do a float, for example, r.
color.r
If you do this, the
The first one, this one, is ready to be taken.
What else?
g Of course you can do this, and
When it's like this, rg... Wrong.
You can do this with rgb.
Another little interesting use for it.
For example, let's do vec4 color2.
color.rbga or something like that.
These b and g values can be used to flip over
This rgba and...
There's another one called xyzw.
There is one more thing that is used in this vUV
What was it again?
stpq.
It's called stpq.
As for this Swizzle to use during this texture
This st is the standard way to use it, so
I'm sure it's used when you see other people's sample code or something.
In fact, using rgb for the colors and xyz for the coordinate system is only possible with
I think it's because it's easy to understand.
If you put in xy or something like that instead of this st, you get the same result.
But it gets a little confusing.
For colors, you can use rgba and xyz for coordinates.
I think it's a good idea to use st for textures.
Okay, I'll leave you with this for a moment.
I'd like to actually write the code.
First of all, write something like vUV.st
0.0, 0.0, 1.0 and
I write it like this.
Oh, something is wrong.
This one.
This will be a vUV.s, not a st
You see, this is what happens when you do this.
This s is basically the x-direction and t is the y-direction, but
As you can see, there's a lot of zero to one information in here.
All the other g's and b's are zero, so I'm not sure what the value of this red is
This is where the visualization comes in.
From blackish to bright red.
Zero to one information.
If you have a color depending on the value of x
It comes down to this.
Just a quick glance at this and I don't know what I'm doing well.
Some of you may say
This is a TouchDesigner instancing of
I'd like to express myself a bit.
What we're doing.
Let's make it a little bigger once.
There's a grid, and this grid is 20x20.
It's a bit smaller than the one we're doing in that Shader.
There's a 20x20 grid.
I'm going to take this as the default, where it's at -0.5 to 0.5.
I'm placing them at 0 to 1.
Zero and one, and that's a one too.
I'd say this is one and one.
Make this SOP a CHOP.
I'm using it for Instancing.
There are a lot of little boxes.
That's how it works.
Here's what this looks like when you open it up a bit
You'll see a row of 20x20 boxes
What we want to do here is
Geometry now Instancing all of these positions in Instancing.
You're placing the t in translate.
tx is this way, ty is that way
That's the way it's supposed to work.
I'd like to add some color information here
rgba, so tx to r
Let me in.
I want to put zeros in everything else.
I'll put an unchanged z in there.
It's like this.
I think it's easier to understand this way.
It's changing from black to red.
This one has 200 pixels.
If this is a GLSL, it's going to be processed all at the same time.
All of these pixels are processed in one frame.
That's how it works.
This code alone will move all the pixels at the same time
It's a bit strange, though.
That's the language.
I just did the x-direction.
This time I would like to express this with Green
The y-coordinates.
If you set it to 0 and put a t here
Now, from the bottom of this one up, it's going to increase from 0 to 1.
So you have the green value of this t in there.
Here's what I mean by this.
It's probably easier to understand if you look at the chop here.
Same with this one, x.
Here's the y in this case.
So it's a little bit more than 20 pieces each.
Now tz, ty.
The x's are all zeros.
It's a state of affairs where you have only y numbers.
It's like this.
When this is happening here.
In short, it's black to green from the bottom.
Here, these numbers are
Increasingly, little by little.
Here's a zero and 20 zeros in a row, and here's one that's a little closer to green.
It's getting to be more and more of a thing.
The final figure is this green one.
It's right here at the top.
This is what it looks like when you do it vertically and horizontally.
I'd like to put both x and y in this.
In addition to this, you can add the r information
That's how you get this kind of gradient.
In the x direction, it's like a red 0 to 1.
Now we have a 0 to 1 in the y direction as well.
It turns yellow here.
A state where r and g are 1
rgb 1, 1, 0 would be here
This instance can be expressed in the same way, with the
In this case, if you already put tx in the
I can make these things.
Here's one for you.
This Fragment Shader has 0 to 1 in it.
I'm sure you understand.
This time.
Using this value that changes from 0 to 1, you can use
I just showed you.
I'd like to create an image of the stripes.
I'm sure there are many ways to do this.
In this case, we'll use a function called sin
I'll make something else up.
GLSL
When I say sin function, I'm talking about a trigonometric function or something like that.
I'm sure you'll all remember this.
Like this.
This is what we call a "sin wave".
As it varies from -1 to 1 depending on the incoming value.
This is what a sin wave looks like when it changes so smoothly.
Let's use this value to represent the color
That's what I'm saying, but...
I'd like to give it a shot.
Now type in "sin".
I'd like to use the x-coordinates I just used.
vUV.st and
I'll put it this way.
Oh, it's broken.
Not "st", but "s", like this.
Oh, okay.
This will get the transparency in there.
I think I'll fix it at 1 transparency.
For that reason.
Set this color to vec3 once.
I don't know if this will work.
I don't like it.
It goes something like this.
This TDAOutputSwizzle takes a value of vec4, so the
I made it in vec4 and here's the vec3 color information
I see there's a rgb in there.
The colors have the same information for all the main rgb's.
Alpha has always been fixed at 1.
That's what it's supposed to be.
All rgb's are the same, so basically.
It's a black to white grayscale image.
I can turn this one off for a minute.
Let's get rid of it.
So this vUV.s is basically a number between 0 and 1.
This is now a 0 to 1 sin function.
So the results are in there.
To make this a good border.
I'm going to crunch the numbers.
I found a calculator that calculates the sin function here
The value that goes in here is calculated by putting in radians, so
For example, if you do a sin0, you'll get a 0.
This zero is what's going on here on the left side right now.
Think of this as a zero.
So there's 0 to 1 in here.
If this is set to 0.
It's simply going to be 0 to 0.84 here.
Let's say, two.
The number 0.90929743 will come in.
For example, if you feel like you want to include these kinds of numbers
If you simply double x
This is how you do it.
It will have a value between 0 and 0.9.
I'm a little confused as it is.
If you put the number 3.14 in here, for example.
When you put in the numbers with this, you basically go from roughly 0 to 1 like this.
We got a number that looks like it's going to go back to zero one more time.
So there's going to be a pause here.
Let me put it this way.
Here's the number from here to here.
We're in a situation where we've gone from 0 to 1 to get here.
And if you add in a number like 6.28, which is twice the number of pi here.
Come from 0 to 1 from here.
1 to 0, -1, and 0 in.
That's what the numbers are so far in.
In the GLSL, all numbers below zero are supposed to be the same as zero.
You can't put it in color.
It's all in black there, so you have to go from 0 to 1, 1 to 0.
From there, we go from 0 to -1 and then back to 0 again, which is what we have in here.
Now we're going to add more numbers here.
Two rounds like this, it's like having two waves of this.
It goes something like this.
We don't need to use this value of pi, we can just put 10 or something in there.
Oh, I'm back in a bit.
If you put 20 or so in here.
As the waves grew and grew and grew.
It comes down to this.
The more you put in any number, the more you put in, the more you get.
As the cycle gets faster and faster.
Just like this. Come on.
It's like this.
0 to 1, and then -1.
So the expression is repeated.
I think you can see it here.
The black part is inevitably bigger than this white part.
Because it's this basic 1 to -1 cycle that repeats
We'll go from 0 to -1 and everything from -1 to 0 will be completely black.
That means there are more black areas.
I'll put the appropriate numbers in here.
I thought a border like this would be cool.
I think this is still pretty good.
I'd like to try to move this, or rather, an animation this time.
If it's a standalone GLSL, it's a standalone, or maybe just this one thing.
I can't save the previous frame, or variables from the previous frame, or anything like that, but
We're trying to get things moving here.
I'd like to give this the variable of time.
At times like this, you know.
When you send variables from the CPU to the GPU and GLSL.
We'll use something called a uniform variable
It first declares the uniform variable in the code
So this is the one we already have in our sample.
With the word "uniform" at the top of my head.
This is a mold.
I'm going to spend some time on this one, so I'm going to keep it on float.
For example, you can create a variable like this
I don't care what it is.
That's my rule.
You've created a variable called uniform time
For example, in ShaderToy, it's iGlobalTime.
The service, or the software.
I mean, there's some etiquette to it.
Basically, I can handle anything.
Use what you're comfortable with.
This is how I use it now.
Now how do we get to this value?
So that's what I'm saying.
I'm going to have to manually write this in here.
There are some useful features...
I'll save one.
If you press the "Load Uniform Name" button
It will automatically go in here.
You know what I'm declaring here.
One click here.
I'm not in it.
Is there something wrong with that?
Well, no, it's just that there's not much in there.
I'd like to do it manually.
Put it in here like uTime.
So that's the Uniform name to match this name.
As you can see, there are four of them.
I can use it as a vec4.
You can also use it in this first one in the form of a float
Here's the usual absTime.frame
I put these in.
Now that we have this value in here, the
This value can be used in GLSL
For example, if you put it at +, you can put it at
So this is why the animation runs.
I thought it was a bit fast.
Let me put it this way.
What's going on is basically
It's like this wave is moving.
This is the kind of wave that is created when such a value is entered against this sin.
So that's what I'm saying.
I'm moving it like this.
This is the kind of image I'm looking for.
This, of course, is.
I'm doing the colors on the side now.
You can easily turn it upside down like this
If you change this speed.
And the animation will be faster.
If you change the numbers here, you can change the cycle.
That's how it works.
This time, sir.
We all learned about GLSL's coordinate system in TouchDesigner.
I made a little animation.
I'll see you next time.
I wish I could make things a little more complicated.
In addition to the YouTube tutorials on TDSW
We offer live streaming workshops about two weekends a month.
If you are interested in TDSW through the tutorial
Please come and visit us at our live streaming workshops!
Also, TDSW uses Patreon
The current plan to support the creation of YouTube and unlimited workshop videos
There are three plans: Workshop Video and Live Streaming Video Plan
It is more profitable than attending the workshop by itself.
I hope you will consider it.
Please check out the link in the summary section!
Thank you for watching.
Please subscribe to the channel if you'd like.
goodbye
[Music]